A Guide to the Virginia Citizens Consumer Council Records, 1969-1993
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Citizens Consumer Council Records, 1969-1993
The Library of Virginia
40992
7.65 cu. ft. (17 boxes)
Virginia Citizens Consumer Council
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Virginia Citizens Consumer Council, Richmond, Virginia, 7 January 2004.
Biographical Information
The Virginia Citizens Consumer Council (VCCC) is a non-profit volunteer association founded in 1966 by three women from Northern Virginia who were concerned about rising food and utilities costs. The organization promotes and represents the rights and interests of the consumer in Virginia by advocating pro-consumer positions in regulatory and legislative issues. They also participate in hearings and proceedings at the local, state and federal levels, and educate the community about consumer issues.
Scope and Content
The records are arranged alphabetically in 17 boxes and include annual reports, brochures, by-laws, correspondence, legislation, memoranda, minutes, newspaper clippings, newsletters, press releases, publications, reports, speeches, and surveys, documenting the history of VCCC's contribution to Virginia's consumer rights. Includes information on legislation to promote child car safety, passage of Virginia's new car "lemon-laws," successful challenges to allow prescription drug price advertising, lawsuits brought to restrict the availability of junk food in schools, efforts to stop Virginia Electric and Power Company (VEPCO) rate increases, support of plain language laws, regulation of health spas, and reform of ground beef labeling.
The Board of director's minute files are a good resource for annual reports, finances, meeting agendas, membership lists, memoranda, minutes, notes, organizational charts, press releases, resolutions, and treasurer's reports detailing VCCC's yearly activities. Several committees were established by VCCC to confront diverse issues, including the Complaint Committee, Legislative Committee, Supermarket Committee, and Toy Safety Committee. These committee files include correspondence, memoranda, minutes, notes, and press releases. The Legislative Committee, 1973-1991, includes correspondence, copies of legislative bills, information on lobbying efforts in the Virginia General Assembly, voting records of legislative members, and VCCC legislative agendas. The Complaint Committee, 1970-1975, gathered information on consumer complaints against various companies. The committee published the Consumer Complaint Action Guide, which provided consumers information about where and who to write for complaints about products (such as appliance repair, home construction, magazine subscriptions, and the postal service).
Information is included about the Dial-A-Consumer service, a 24 hour a day answering service which contained weekly messages concerning consumer safety alerts, general information on consumer topics, and notices of meetings or seminars, 1976-1977. Included is a notebook from 1977 listing the weekly messages. Also included are agendas, brochures, correspondence, memoranda, and programs for the annual VCCC Consumer Conference, 1988-1989; memoranda regarding grants from the Consumer Federation of America, 1987-1990; and correspondence, newsletters, and press releases from VCCC chapters (Northern Virginia, Richmond, Roanoke, and Williamsburg). The VCCC also initiated a number of lawsuits in their efforts to protect the Virginia consumer and the collection contains clippings, correspondence, legal judgments and statements relating to the suits. The organization was involved with lawsuits against VEPCO, the Virginia State Board of Pharmacy, Department of Agriculture, the American Bar Association, the Virginia State Bar, and Virginia Supreme Court.
Included are copies of newspaper clippings, 1970-1991, regarding initiatives by the VCCC to inform and protect consumers. Included are articles written by members of the VCCC entitled, "Consumer's Voice" and "Buy-Lines" in various Northern Virginia newspapers, 1975-1976. These article inform readers about pool safety, shopping in supermarkets, banking practices, new legislation, red food dye #2, surveys on cold medicine prices at local drug stores, UPC codes, donations to charity, tenant rights, how to proceed with complaints, new rules for mail order firms, salesman insurance laws, medical malpractice laws, and safety with zip-top cans.
Also included is an almost complete run of the VCCC newsletter entitled, "Voice of the Virginia Consumer," 1970-1993. The publication, Handbook (1976), includes a directory of members, board meeting schedules, general resolutions, board pledge, and VCCC bylaws and constitution. Numerous publications are also included such as, Citizen Inflation Action Handbook, Forming Consumer Organizations, Getting your Day in General District Court, and Training Consumer Leaders.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Action/Inaction: A Guide to the Virginia Legislature, Notes, misc., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Action program committee, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Action for child transportation safety (ACTS) chapters, 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Automobile insurance, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Automobile lemon law, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Awards, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Board of dentistry, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Board of directors minute files, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Board of directors minute files, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Board of directors minute files, 1972 January-September (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Board of directors minute files, 1972 October-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Board of directors minute files, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Board of directors minute files, 1974 January-June (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Board of directors minute files, 1974 July-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Board of directors minute files, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Board of directors minute files, 1976 January-June (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Board of directors minute files, 1976 July-December (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Board of directors minute files, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Board of directors minute files, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Board of directors minute files, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Board of directors minute files, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Board of directors minute files, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Board of directors minute files, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Board of directors minute files, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Board of directors minute files, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Board of directors minute files, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Board of directors minute files, 1987 January-June (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Board of directors minute files, 1987 July-December (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Board of directors minute files, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Board of directors minute files, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Board of directors minute files, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Board of directors minute files, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Board of directors minute files, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Board of directors minute files, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Board of directors, list, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Boycotts, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Brochures and flyers, 1973-1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Brochures, Drafts, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Bylaws and constitution, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Bylaws, Drafts, notes, and miscellaneous, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Chain Store Public Relations Conference, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Chapter charter certificates, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Chapters (VCCC), Misc., 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Chapters (VCCC), Newport News Chapter, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Chapters (VCCC), Northern Virginia Chapter, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Chapters (VCCC), Northern Virginia Chapter, Clippings, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Chapters (VCCC), Northern Virginia Chapter, Newsletters, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Chapters (VCCC), Northern Virginia Chapter, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Chapters (VCCC), Price William Chapter, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Chapters (VCCC), Richmond Chapter, 1971-1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Chapters (VCCC), Roanoke Chapter, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Chapters (VCCC), Tidewater Chapter, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Chapters (VCCC), Tidewater Chapter, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Chapters (VCCC), Williamsburg Chapter, 1970-1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Co., 1974 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Clippings, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Clippings, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Clippings, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Clippings, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Clippings, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Clippings, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Clippings, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Clippings, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Clippings, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Clippings, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Community Nutrition Institute, Lawsuit, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- Consulting, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Community Awareness Day, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Consumer Activity Banking and Insurance (CABIN), 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Consumer Complaint Committee, Activities, minutes, etc., 1970-1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Consumer Complaint Committee, Consumer Complaint Action Guide, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Consumer Conference, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Consumer Conference, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Consumer Congress of Virginia, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Consumer Education and Awareness Committee, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Consumer Federation of America grants, 1987-1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Consumer Leadership Conference Booklet and Planning Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Consumers Union, 1970-1978 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Contracts, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Dial-A-Consumer, 1972-1977 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Drug prices, 1972-1976 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Energy conscious Christmas, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Energy policy, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- False advertising issues, 1971-1974 (Box 9, Folder 1=)
- Flea market, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Food Day, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Fundraising events, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Funeral directors, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Golden Coathanger Awards, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Ground beef blast, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Handbook, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Health Planning Council of Northern Virginia, Doctors director, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Health Planning Council of Northern Virginia, Doctors director, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Health Planning Council of Northern Virginia, Doctors director, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Health regulatory reform, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Health spa legislation, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Iowa beef industry council, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Internal Revenue Service (IRS), Correspondence with, 1974-1976 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Lawyers committee and directory, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Legislative issues, General, 1973-1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Legislative issues, General, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Legislative issues, General, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Legislative issues, General, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Legislative issues, General, 1985-1987 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Legislative issues, General, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Legislative issues, General, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Liability insurance, 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Liability insurance, Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Lobbyists, 1988-1992 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Membership, 1976-1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1983-1984 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, 1991-1993 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Newsletters, Voice of the Virginia Consumer, Distribution list, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Plain language laws, Articles, pamphlets, etc., 1986 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Plain language laws, "How Plain English Works for Business: 12 Case Studies," 1984 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Plain language laws, Simply Stated newsletters, 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Power companies, 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Press releases, 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Press releases, Copies, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Press releases, Drafts, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Press releases, Copies, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Press releases, Drafts, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Press releases, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Press releases, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Press releases, 1976-1978 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Press releases, 1983-1990 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Press releases, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Prescription drug pricing, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Publications, Action/Inaction: A Guide to the Virginia Legislature, prepared by the Legislative Committee of the VCCC, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Publications, Attorney's Directory for Arlington County, published by Consumers Union and VCCC, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Publications, Citizen Inflation Action Handbook, prepared by Consumers Opposed to Inflation in the Necessities (The COIN Campaign), ca. 1978 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Publications, Conducting the Consumer Survey: A Primer for Volunteers with Special Sections on Interviewing and on Telephone Surveying, by Glen H. Mitchell with Mark L. Mitchell, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Publications, Getting your day in General District Court, published by the Fairfax County Dept. of Consumer Affairs, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Publications, Forming Consumer Organizations, prepared by the President's Committee on Consumer Interests, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Publications, Hearings before the Subcommittee for Consumers of the Committee on Commerce United States Senate, 94th Congress, 2nd Session, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Publications, An Invitation to Consumers, prepared by VCCC, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
- Publications, The National Seminar on EFT Consumer/Industry/Government, held by the Virginia Citizens Consumer Foundation and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Publications, Report: COCO National Conference on Professional, Occupational, and Institutional Licensing & the Consumer, sponsored by Conference of Consumer Organizations (COCO) and VCCC, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Publications, Training Consumer Leaders: Planning and implementing a consumer leadership conference, by Ruth D. Harris, Laura Horowitz, and Lynn Jordan, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Publications, Virginia State Board of Pharmacy vs. Virginia Citizens Consumer Council, in the Supreme Court of the United States, October term 1974: Motion to Dismiss, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 16)
- Public members on boards, 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Real estate, 1989-1990 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Springfield Mall Committee, 1973-1976 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Stamps, 1969-1972 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- State Corporation Commission, Constitution of Virginia, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Status of Women, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Student action, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Studies, Consumer Study of Electronic Funds transfer, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Studies, Proposed trade regulation rule on over-the-counter antacids, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Studies, Report on bypass and drop off in the state of Washington: Findings and Recommendation, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Studies, White paper on credit insurance, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 11)
- Supermarket Committee, 1971-1976 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Surveys, Automobiles, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Surveys, Legislative members, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 14)
- Surveys, VCCC membership, 1973-1992 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Surveys, Miscellaneous, 1973-1977 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Tax exempt application, 1975-1985 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Tax reform, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Telecommunications Conference, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Telephone Solicitation Ethics Council, Code of Ethics, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Telephone Solicitation Ethics Council, Correspondence, etc., 1973-1978 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Testimony of Judy Kory, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Testimony of the VCCC on the Board of Nursing, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Tort reform, 1986-1987 (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Tort reform, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Tort reform, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Toy Safety Committee, 1972-1975 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Truth squads, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- UPC Code, 1975-1976 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- U.S. Postal Service bulk mail permits, 1974-1976 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- VEPCO Stock certificate and dividends, 1975-1983 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Volunteer meeting, 1974-1976 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- WNVT Television (Channel 53), 1972 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Women with a purpose, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 9)